# **Chase Stokes**

cstokes@ischool.berkeley.edu chasejstokes.github.io

I am a mixed methods researcher situated at the intersection of language and visualization. My work focuses on the challenges and opportunities presented by multimodal information displays, delving into how language shapes the reader's experience and understanding. I aim to identify best practices for integrating text and visualizations and improve the effectiveness of information communication.

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD. in Information Science

2021 – present

University of California at Berkeley

Advisor: Marti Hearst, PhD.

Relevant coursework: HCI Research, UX Research, Information

Visualization and Presentation, Interface Aesthetics

B.A. in Psychology and Gender and Sexuality Studies

2021

Northwestern University, GPA 3.92 Advisor: Steven Franconeri, PhD.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Intern Summer 2023

Tableau

Graduate Student Researcher 2021 – present

Hearst Lab, UC Berkeley

Undergraduate Research Assistant 2018 – 2021

Visual Thinking Lab, Northwestern University

Data Collector Summer 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Research Assistant 2019 – 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Summer Intern Summer 2019

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- **Stokes, C.,** Bearfield, C. X., & Hearst, M.A. (2023). The Role of Text in Visualizations: How Annotations Shape Perceptions of Bias and Influence Predictions. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Bearfield, C. X., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2023). What Does the Chart Say? Grouping Cues Guide Viewer Comparisons and Conclusions in Bar Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** Setlur, V., Cogley, B., Satyanarayan, A., and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Striking a Balance: Reader Takeaways and Preferences when Integrating Text and Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Why More Text is (Often) Better: Themes from Reader Preferences for Integration of Charts and Text, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.,** Kim, Y. S., & Franconeri, S. (2022). Seeing What You Believe or Believing What You See? Belief Biases Correlation Estimation. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2021). Give Text A Chance: Advocating for Equal Consideration for Language and Visualization, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

#### POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS

- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Hearst, M.A. (2022, Nov). Driving Reader Interpretations with Text Annotations in Data Visualizations. Poster presented at Society for Judgement and Decision Making, San Diego, CA.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.**, Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2021, May). Visual Salience and Grouping Cues Guide Relation Perception in Visual Data Displays. Poster presented at Virtual Vision Sciences Society.
- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Franconeri, S. (2020, May). Seeing What You Want: Prior Belief Biases Perception of Correlation in Scatterplots. Poster presented at Virtual 32nd APS Annual Convention, Chicago, IL.
- Callahan, C., **Stokes, C.,** & Lawrence, E. (2020, May). Modifying the Relationship Quality Interview for Sexual and Gender Minority Couples. Accepted Poster Presentation at the 8th Annual LGBTQ Research Symposium at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. (Conference Canceled)

### FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS, AND HONORS

Fellowships	
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Recipient	2023 - present
Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship Honorable Mention	2023
School of Information Fellowship for Doctoral Study	2021 – 2022

#### Awards

National Merit Finalist 2017 – 2021

#### Honors

Departmental Honors - Psychology Phi Beta Kappa	2021 2021
Northwestern University Dean's List with Distinction	2017 – 2021
GRANTS	
Northwestern Summer Undergraduate Research Grant (\$3,500) Visual Grouping Affords Different Comparison Patterns in Visualized Data	Summer 2020
Northwestern Academic Year Research Grant (\$1,000)  Variations in Conclusions Afforded by Chart Type	2020
STUDENT LEADERSHIP ROLES	
Underrepresented Applicant Feedback Program Co-coordinated initiative to provide feedback to underrepresented PhD. ap	2023 oplicants
NorCal Visualization Group Organizer Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars	2022 – 2023
Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.)	2019 – 2020
Participant Coordinator,	2019 – 2020
Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator  Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.)	2018 – 2019
Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance	2018 – 2019
STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS	
Association for Computing Machinery, Student Member	2021 – present
Psychonomic Society, Student Member	2021 – present
Cognitive Science Society, Student Member	2021 – present
Society for Judgment and Decision Making, Student Member	2021 – present
AD-HOC REVIEWS	
Ocean and Coastal Research	2023
Journal of Official Statistics	2023
Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG)	2023
ACM Computer-Human Interaction (CHI)	2022-2023
IEEE VIS Short Papers	2022
Creativity & Cognition	2021
SERVICE AND OUTREACH	
25th Anniversary of the Master of Information Management and Systems	s 2022

## Facilitated two 30-minute panels

PhD. Applicant Feedback Program Provided feedback to underrepresented applicants	2022
Student Volunteer at IEEE VIS	2022
Washington University School of Medicine Mini-Medical School Panelist	2019, 2021
Alternative Student Breaks	2017 – 2019
College Mentors for Kids	2017 – 2019

REFERENCES PROVIDED UPON REQUEST